Everybody. All right, today's דף, Daf, as was said, is
ס"ה, Samech Hey, but we start on ס"ד עמוד ב' Samech Dalet
Amud Bet on the משנה Mishnah
and let's take a look. Very fascinating דף Daf today.
מצוות העומר להביא מן הקרוב, Mitzvas HaOmer lehavi min hakarov, the מצוה
Mitzvah is to bring from the grain that is near ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
לא ביכר הקרוב לירושלים, Lo biker hakarov l'Yerushalayim, if the grain near
ירושלים Yerushalayim was not yet ripe, מביאין אותו מכל מקום, mev'iyin oso
mikol makom, bring it from everywhere. Everywhere is of course limited to
anywhere in Israel. גמרא Gemara said earlier in an explicit משנה Mishnah
that the עומר Omer can only come from grain from Israel, but
ideally from grain closer to
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. מעשה שבא העומר ודגגות צריפים, Maiseh shebohaomer ve'digagot tzifim, there
was a time when the עומר Omer had to come from a
place called גגות צריפים, Gagot Tzifim, the roofs of צריפים, Tzifim, which
are like teepees, but anyway that was the name of a village
or something. ושתי הלחם מבקעת עין סוכר, Ushtei halechem mibik'at ein socher,
and the type that they only had ripe wheat grain in a
place called עין סוכר Ein Socher when it was time for the
שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. Okay. גמרא, Gemara, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's
the reason that you're supposed to bring from the nearby grain? איבעית
אימא משום כרמל, Ibayis teima mishum carmel, because we do a דרשה
drasha on כרמל carmel because it says you bring the עומר Omer
from כרמל carmel which we read as רך ומלא, rach vemalei, that
the grain has to be full and soft. So the closer you
bring it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the softer, you know, the riper, the
grain, not riper, fresher, the grain is, it doesn't get hard yet.
רך Rach means, no, they play words, this is רך rach as
different from soft. So כר car is רך rach and מלא malei
like full and ripe and soft though not, you know, fresh. ואיבעית
אימא, Ve'ibayis teima, and if you want, משום דאין מעבירין על המצוות.
mishum d'ein ma'avirin al hamitzvos. You don't pass over the מצוות. mitzvos.
If you have the grain that's right here, to pass by it
and go somewhere else, you're מעביר על המצוות. ma'avir al hamitzvos. Now
תוספות Tosafos has a whole discussion, there's a whole סוגיא sugya about
what constitutes מעביר על המצוות. ma'avir al hamitzvos. You know, classic example
for example for מעביר על המצוות ma'avir al hamitzvos and אין מעבירין
ein ma'avirin and it's important would be we learned before, you know,
earlier in מנחות Menachos that you put on your תפילין של יד
tefillin shel yad before your תפילין של ראש. tefillin shel rosh. What
happens if you stick your hand in your תפילין tefillin bag and
you take out by accident your תפילין של ראש? tefillin shel rosh?
Okay, now there, אין מעבירין על המצוות ein ma'avirin al hamitzvos שיקרה
she-yirtzei that you should put on your תפילין של ראש tefillin shel
rosh first. You don't put it aside and get תפילין של יד.
tefillin shel yad. However, there you actually do for the sake of
the importance of having the יד yad on first, actually do pass
over it and switch the order. But that's where those two things
come in conflict. The idea that you encountered the מצוה mitzvah so
you put it aside in order to do another one. That's the
principle of אין מעבירין על המצוות. ein ma'avirin al hamitzvos. It's a
little strange here, because here you are not not doing one מצוה
mitzvah for the sake of another, you are trying to do one
מצוה mitzvah ideally. Now you could still say that you have an
opportunity to use this grain, you don't set aside this grain to
say, 'well, you know, I'll find some other better grain from somewhere
else.' But you know, it's not always that simple. Like if you
imagine, let's say a mile to the east of ירושלים Yerushalayim is
ripe grain, but ten miles to the west of it is also
ripe grain that's a better quality. If I leave ירושלים Yerushalayim and
I go to the west, I'm not exactly מעביר על המצוות ma'avir
al hamitzvos because there's closer grain to the east, right? So the
idea that it's not even if you encounter it and you set
it aside, but that you're sort of able to say, 'well, this
is the closer one, the more available one, even though I haven't
yet encountered it and therefore I should go this way rather than
the other way.' It's interesting that that's included in the principle of
אין מעבירין על המצוות, ein ma'avirin al hamitzvos, it seems to be.
Right. I mean, you're right, I drew the scenario that you didn't
have to encounter it yet. Okay, but it does seem that it
includes even that
case. Yeah. I thought you were saying all things being equal you
go closer to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but you're saying is even if all
things are not equal. אוי אוי, Oi oy, no, I think the
סתם המשנה stam hamishnah is that as long as it's ripe and
it satisfies the right criteria. Of course you might, you're right, sometimes
you do pass something over just like yesterday, you שחט shechted an
animal on שבת Shabbos for a קרבן Korban and there's a nice
one here, we're going to ignore this to do the nicer one.
It's an excellent point. You're right, I was somehow assuming that, you
know,
the משנה mishnah meant even all things not being equal. If it
is all things being equal, then of course it makes total sense.
Okay,
yeah. So, what was
the... the
ליתלי litlei of כרמל? carmel?
I'd have to look at the English translation. I don't know actually.
I think as some, some... what do your Englishes have? Anything? What
do you have in English, what does it say there? Oh, I
do. You'll tell us. All right, let's start with a very basic
question. Do they go to somebody's private field or do they go
to like a public field? Private field, it seems. So why didn't
the משנה Mishnah just have its own thing for this? You'd think
if you do it every year, they'd have it- it's a lot
easier not to have your own thing. Wait till you find somebody
has good grain and then you get the, you know what I'm
saying? Doesn't have to be to tend the whole field and then
maybe send it for that thing. Plump. Well, that's certainly- okay, plump
is certainly a good word. Apparently the sense in which the גמרא'ס
Gemara's reading it, whether that is- can't trust Artscroll to give you
like the, you know, פשט. pshat. They're reading it through the lens
of the גמרא. Gemara. But anyway. Alright, let's go on. Somebody can
look at, you know, different... you'll look at a different translation. Now,
מעשה שבא עומר מגגות צריפין. Maaseh sheba omer migagot tzerifin. The עומר
omer came from this place called גגות צריפין Gagot Tzerifin once. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now we're going to find out the story about
how it came down. כשצרו מלכי בית חשמונאי זה על זה, Keshetzaru
malkhei beit Hashmonai zeh al zeh,
when the kings of the בית חשמונאי Beit Hashmonai were laying siege
one to the other, והיה הורקנוס מבחוץ ואריסטובלוס מבפנים, vehayah Hurkanus mibachutz
veAristobulus mibifnim,
הורקנוס Hurkanus was outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim laying siege to ירושלים Yerushalayim
and אריסטובלוס Aristobulus was in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. These actually they were descendants
of the חשמונאים Hashmonaim and they were yes and they were fighting
against each other about who gets to be the king,
and, you know, different ones of them at different stages were soliciting
the aid of the Romans or, no, it was before the Romans,
excuse me, of the Seleucids. Anyway,
it's
actually and the גמרא'ס Gemara's description is quite accurate because it says
when they were צרין זה על זה, tzarin zeh al zeh, והיה,
vehayah, because if you read your Josephus, which of course I do
every night, but I did in preparation for this שיעור, shiur, it
actually it reversed itself. First it used to be that
הורקנוס Hurkanus was on the inside and אריסטובלוס Aristobulus was on the
outside and אריסטובלוס Aristobulus conquered ירושלים Yerushalayim and he became king and
then and then it reversed and then and now we have our
scenario which is that אריסטובלוס Aristobulus is on the inside and הורקנוס
Hurkanus is outside. So the sense the גמרא'ס Gemara's phrasing if you
look pay attention to it is very appropriate that it sounds like
it was going back and forth. They were צרין זה על זה
tzarin zeh al zeh and in this moment this is the way
it was in this moment. Well no, not a dialogue, like a
vacillating war. So at this moment, I mean it wasn't all in
the one time, it wasn't all one war. One first won and
then the other sort of regrouped and gained troops and alliances whatever.
Anyway, at this time הורקנוס Hurkanus was on the outside and אריסטובלוס
Aristobulus was on the inside. Okay. בכל יום ויום היו משלשלים להן
דינרים בקופה. Bekhol yom vayom hayu meshalshelim lahen dinarim bekupa. Every day
they would lower down דינרים dinarim through a basket from the walls
of ירושלים Yerushalayim ומעלים להם תמידים uma'alin lahem temidim and the troops
on the outside even though they were laying siege were nice enough
to be sending up lambs to use as תמידים temidim because they
absolutely at least it was one thing who gets to be king
it's another thing the temple that's our central you know place of
worship we at least acknowledge that so they would send up תמידים.
temidim.
Okay. היה שם זקן אחד. Hayah sham zaken echad. There was a
certain
old man known as forty days in advance or well that's a
good question since they were מקיף makif on that שהיה מכיר בחכמת
יוונית. shehayah makkir bechochmat Yevanit. He knew the חכמת יוונית, chochmat Yevanit,
the Greek wisdom. From the context it is clear I'll talk in
a minute what the how this is used at another גמרא Gemara
but from the context it's clear that it means that it was
some way that allowed him to communicate with others without being detected.
Sort of like Morse code. Maybe it literally means the Greek language
maybe it means תוספות Tosafot says that it was maybe certain types
of signals you know or Morse code type of thing anyway some
form of communication the Greek wisdom. לעז להם בחכמת יוונית. La'az lahem
bechochmat Yevanit. He spoke to them but again the whole word לעז
la'az is almost like to speak in a vernacular. He communicated to
them this was a guy on the inside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. He
was basically a traitor and he was communicating to the people on
the outside and the way he did it without being discovered was
using חכמת יוונית chochmat Yevanit again whatever exactly that is. So he
communicated to them in this form of Greek wisdom. ואמר להם. Veamar
lahem. He said to the people on the outside כל זמן שעסוקים
בעבודה אין נמסרים בידכם. kol zeman she'asukim ba'avodah ein nimsarim beyadekhem.
As long as while they are still working doing the עבודה Avodah
properly worshipping in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash that will protect them
they will not be handed over to you. The whole idea is
quite strange because it's not like a particular piece of secret information
that he had that you had to be on the inside to
hand over to people on the outside right? I mean if it's
a religious belief that if you're worshipping in the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash God is going to protect you. You know a little while
ago the troops on the outside were on the inside and they
were the ones in possession of ירושלים Yerushalayim so it's a little
strange the way things set up like he's secretly passing on this
little bit of information. Maybe it's the morale thing. Oh oh that's
interesting. It's not metaphysical he's saying you know that their morale depends
on it. That's a nice פשט. pshat. I don't know if it
sits with the larger theme here which is but let's take a
look that's a nice פשט. pshat. Okay. למחר. Lemachar. So the next
day שלשלו להן דינרים בקופה. shilshlu lahen dinarim bekupa. They lowered down
דינרים dinarim in the basket והעלו להם חזיר vehe'elu lahem chazir and
instead of putting a lamb in it they put a pig in
it. כיון שהגיע לחצי חומה. Keivan shehiggia lechatzi chomah. When the pig
got halfway up the wall נעץ צפרניו בחומה. na'atz tzipornav bachomah. He
you know he put his talons anyway talons whatever his nails into
the wall ונזדעזעה ארץ ישראל ארבע מאות. venizda'aza Eretz Yisrael arba me'ot.
ארבע מאה פרסה על ארבע מאה פרסה arba meah parsa al arba
meah parsa and the whole land of Israel shook 400 parasangs by
400 parasangs. This is that's a measurement the גמרא Gemara gives for
the size of the land of Israel, not exactly accurate but whatever.
Entire land of Israel shook. One minute, let's finish the story. Okay,
באותה שעה אמרו, beotah shaah amru, at that moment they said, ארור
שיגדל חזירים, arur sheyegadel chazirim, cursed be the person that raises pigs,
וארור שילמד בנו חכמת יוונית, vearur sheyelamed beno chochmat yevanit, and
cursed be the person that teaches his son the Greek wisdom. Yeah,
I'll talk about that in a minute. ועל אותה שעה שנינו. veal
otah shaah shaninu.
Now how is this all relevant? Because it was regarding that time
when they were besieged and they were in ירושלים Yerushalayim and they
needed to get their stuff for the קרבנות korbanot from the outside.
So we have a tradition it was during that time that they
could not get the grain from nearby. Now of course that still
means you need some help from people on the outside to get
the grain. But anyway the way רש"י Rashi explains it is what
you do when you're laying siege to a city is you burn
all of the fields nearby, scorched the earth so that they don't
have where to draw sustenance from.
So and presumably though they were still getting the assistance of the
troops on the outside for קרבנות. korbanot. So it was regarding that
time that we taught מעשה שבא עומר מגגות צריפין, maaseh sheba omer
migagot tsrifin, that's when the עומר omer came from גגות צריפין, Gagot
Tsrifin, ושתי הלחם מבקעת עין סוכר, veshtei halechem mibik'at ein socher,
and the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem came from this place of בקעת
עין סוכר. Bik'at Ein Socher. Now maybe it could also be by
the way that maybe it was after they conquered ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
these troops, then they needed to bring the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem
and the עומר, omer, but they had already burned the nearby fields.
That makes it a little bit more understandable that you don't have
to rely on the troops on the outside to bring the שתי
הלחם Shtei HaLechem and the עומר omer which is not part of
the story, so maybe it was after it was conquered. Okay and
now here's another interesting, the story isn't done because there's a nice
little parallel coming up, before it was about this old person telling
them with חכמת יוונית, chochmat yevanit, so let's sort of finish this
story here and then we could go back and analyze. I don't
know what that said. We'll go back and analyze it. Some people
are writing stuff. This is where the עומר omer comes from because
they had to. I'm playing the audio. I can't hear anything about
what? It was during this time that we have this situation in
the משנה Mishna when the tradition said once they had to bring
this עומר omer from this faraway place, גגות צריפין. Gagot Tsrifin. We
have a tradition that occurred during this time when all the nearby
fields were scorched. Okay, so now let's see the end of this
story. Okay, כי מטא עומר, ki mata omer, when the when
they brought when it was time to bring the עומר, omer, לא
הוו ידעי מהיכא לייתיי, lo havu yadei meheicha leityei, they didn't know
where to bring it from because all these nearby fields were scorched.
אכריזו, achrezu, they made an announcement, if anybody knows where there'd be
a good place to get some wheat or excuse me barley for
the עומר, omer, please let us know. Okay, אתא ההוא חרשא, ata
hahu charasha, a certain mute came, actually חרש cheresh often means deaf-mute
but here the emphasis is that he's mute. Hopefully he couldn't have
been too deaf because he heard the announcement, maybe somebody told him.
Anyway, אותיב חדא ידא אאיגרא, oteiv chada yada a-igra,
he put one hand on a roof of some building, וחדא ידא
אצריפא, vechada yada atzerifa, and one hand on the אצריפא atzerifa which
is like a teepee type of a structure. So he did like
this. So אמרו להו, amru lehu, so he said to them
מרדכי, Mordechai, רש"י Rashi says it's the original מרדכי, Mordechai, תוספות Tosafot
says no that would make him a little, that would make him
a little a little old. Right? So anyway but somebody by the
name of מרדכי, Mordechai, it doesn't matter the גמרא Gemara is going
to identify him to the original מרדכי Mordechai anyway in terms of
somebody that is very wise and informed and is a leader. Anyway,
so מרדכי Mordechai said to the other sort of leaders around there
or whoever it was that was trying to get the עומר, omer,
מי איכא
דוכתא דשמה גגות צריפין או צריפין גגות? mi ika duchta deshama Gagot
Tsrifin o Tsrifin Gagot? He said, Oh so does anybody know is
there a place called גגות צריפין Gagot Tsrifin or צריפין גגות Tsrifin
Gagot because he's putting one hand on a roof and one hand
on a? So then they said, Oh yeah טאקא, taka, בדקו ואשכחו,
badku veashkechu, they found yeah there was a place called גגות צריפין
Gagot Tsrifin and therefore they sent and they got the wheat from
there. Now כי בעו לאתויי שתי הלחם, ki bau leatuyei shtei halechem,
when it was time to bring the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, לא
הוו ידעי מהיכא לייתיי, lo havu yadei meheicha leityei,
they didn't know where to bring it from. Where is there a
place where there's right wheat? All the wheat nearby is not available,
it's burned, destroyed. אכריזו, achrezu, they made an announcement. אתא ההוא חרשא,
ata hahu charasha, again this deaf-mute but really this mute person came.
אותיב ידא אעיניה, oteiv yada aeineih, he put one hand on his
eye, right? וחדא ידא אסיכרא, vechada yada asichra, and one hand on
a אסיכרא asichra which I think is basically a hole through which
a door bolt goes. That's called a סוכר. socher. So remember the
place they brought it from was called עין סוכר. Ein Socher. So
anyway, אמר להו מרדכי, amar lehu Mordechai, so מרדכי Mordechai said to
the people around there, ומי איכא דוכתא דשמה עין סוכר או סוכר
עין? umi ika duchta deshama ein socher o socher ein? Hey is
there any place called
עין סוכר Ein Socher or סוכר עין? Socher Ein? בדקו ואשכחו. badku
veashkechu. Okay and they found טאקא taka there was this place called
עין סוכר Ein Socher so that's where they brought it from. Now
there's a certain nice parallel that there was an old person using
secret language to communicate how to get in and how to sort
of do the wrong thing and the pig which led to them
winning but ultimately doing something terrible and now... Yeah, there’s this parallel
about this old person who's not directly communicating signaling, but not old,
oh right, he's a חרש cheresh too. Anyway, this person is not
directly communicating signaling and telling them where they can now actually bring
what they need to bring. So other than noting that parallel, I’m
not sure here about any sort of larger message, but it is
interesting that almost they reversed what they did to get into ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, at least now they’re trying to do the positive and they’re
using these type of some other type of signal in order to
do that. What do you think about the חזיר chazir and the...
yeah, I did want to say about the חזיר chazir something, just
one or two quick things about the חזיר chazir and the Greek
wisdom. I actually made some copies of this, excuse me for a
second, let me look here.
The really interesting thing is that, so, I'm sorry, let me just
connect this point. Okay, so
first of all about the חזיר. chazir. First of all, I do
wonder when you think about the חזיר chazir putting its nails into
the wall,
חז"ל Chazal often point out that the חזיר chazir is the only
non-כשר kosher animal that has split hooves and
but does not chew its cud, and often says like the חזיר
chazir tries to deceive, it shows its toes and says look I’m
כשר, kosher, I’m כשר. kosher. So I do wonder again if the
idea of cleaving its nails in is somehow some type of a
sense about somebody that appears to be כשר kosher trying to get
in and maybe is that the whole message here about these two
brothers and they're fighting and it’s all like this is not how
we imagine what a real Jewish kingship is supposed to be about.
It's obviously so political and nobody’s really being too פרום frum about
anything and there’s so is there some sense of like appearances to
be כשר kosher and trying to get into ירושלים Yerushalayim and take
control and so on.
That’s once. Now another thing I will say is, another thing I
will say is that in Josephus, I don't have time to read
it, I'll post this out post it on the blog. Anyway in
Josephus Antiquities 14:2, again which I read every night. Anyway they have
the story about this whole thing and in this story it’s not
about the חזיר. chazir. Here’s what the story has.
So it says, when the priests and Aristobulus were besieged, it happened
that the feast called the Passover was come at which it is
our custom to offer a number of sacrifices to God. But those
that were with Aristobulus wanted sacrifice and desired that their countrymen without
would furnish them with such sacrifices and assured them that they should
have as much money for them as they should desire. And when
they required them to pay a thousand drachmae for each head of
cattle, Aristobulus and the priests willingly undertook to pay for them accordingly.
And when then and those within let down the money over the
walls, it sounds pretty
similar other than that it’s a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and that
it’s a thousand drachmas, so part of the point is how much
they’re demanding. But when the others had received it they did not
deliver the sacrifices, but arrived at that height of wickedness as to
break the assurances they had given and to be guilty of impiety
towards God by not furnishing those they wanted them with sacrifices. And
when the priests found that they had been cheated and that the
agreements they had made were violated they prayed to God that he
would avenge them on their countrymen. Nor did he delay their punishment
but sent a strong and vehement storm of wind that destroyed the
fruits of the whole country. There you go, no עומר omer and
שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. Till a מודיוס modius of wheat was then
bought, whatever that is, a measure of wheat, for 11 drachmas, so
that’s how expensive wheat was. So there's obviously some very interesting parallels,
right? I mean obviously the money and whatever and destroying the wheat
and so on. Of course there's no pig. So I was wondering
what happened to the pig, how did, maybe Josephus's version is more
accurate than the גמרא's, Gemara's, a little closer to the events, what
happens with the pig and it occurred to me that maybe the
pig does play a role in the whole story of the חשמונאים
Chashmonaim of the Maccabees, because the whole גזירה gezeira of Antiochus was
חלב חזיר... chelev chazir... Yeah, well not just
חלב חזיר... chelev chazir... no no no, the גזירה gezeira of Antiochus
from Maccabees 1 is, the king sent letters by messengers to Jerusalem
and the towns of Judah, he directed them to follow customs strange
to the land, to forbid burnt offerings and sacrifices and drink offerings
in the sanctuary, to profane sabbaths and festivals, to defile the sanctuary
and the priests, to build altars and sacred precincts and shrines for
idols, to sacrifice swine and other unclean animals and leave their sons
uncircumcised. So the idea of swine as
sacrifices is sort of the whole evocative of the whole גזירה gezeira
of Antiochus. So in a way that really even more underscores how
abominable it is what they’re doing. Here they are, these are the
חשמונאים Chashmonaim that have won the war against Antiochus and in their
attempt for power are basically adopting the whole modes of Antiochus are
basically sending them this pig to sacrifice. So I wonder, it seems
to me that maybe that’s how this story with Josephus got this
element of the pig in it, assuming that that’s how it happened,
it could be חז"ל Chazal just had a completely different history of
it that Josephus was closer to the event. So that’s one thing
in terms of thinking about the pig and its significance. The other
thing I just want to say and then I’ll open it to
questions and then move on is so the idea of Greek wisdom.
So,
Saul Lieberman here in his very famous two works, "Greek in Jewish
Palestine" and "Hellenism in Jewish Palestine", so the beginning of "Hellenism in
Jewish Palestine", one of his first articles is the alleged ban on
Greek wisdom. And what does he say the alleged ban because he
points out and תוספות Tosafot already asked this question, here he's cursing
anybody who's
מלמד בנו חכמת יוונית, melamed beno chochmat Yevanit, you have another... Later
it
became a prohibition
anyway. Anyway, what Saul Lieberman says is is if you look at
all the sources, the entire prohibition was מלמד את בנו חכמת יוונית.
melamed et beno chochmat yevanit. To teach somebody who is still young
this and therefore there was a concern that it was maybe, you
know, maybe it would open up the gates of Hellenism to that
person whatever this is obviously it's somehow it was maybe Greek language
or maybe it sort of, you know, what do you call, you
know, some sense of culture and Hellenist, you know, right some way
made Hellenism accessible. And therefore it was a real threat as בנו
beno when you're young and impressionable. If you're an adult already, then
there's no prohibition. The only issue was, you know, the concern about
the ביטול תורה. bitul Torah. Speaking teach בתו חכמת יוונית. bito chochmat
yevanit. Obviously!
Well, his point was not about the ביטול תורה bitul Torah of
בנו beno and the מצוות המעשיות. mitzvot hamasiyot. His point was about
the threat of Hellenism. Okay, so that's anyway what he does with
that. Okay, so some quick questions. Yeah, so my quick quick question
was, it's interesting they said, you know, as long as they're עוסק
בעבודה osek b'avoda it interrupts. Yeah, you know, because you think that
you'd you know, it'd kind of be both ways and be neutral.
They're doing their עבודה avoda but you're helping them, you're giving them
a קרבן. korban. And by you, like, giving them a חזיר chazir
of anything, if I were God, I mean, I'm not God, you
know what I'm saying, but I would go with Gad's point that
it was more about morale than anything else. I mean, you notice
the גמרא Gemara doesn't say, after it says נצורה ירושלים, netzura Yerushalayim,
it doesn't say like all of a sudden they broke into the
חומה choma it doesn't tell you what happened in the next stages
to allow them to. I don't know. It's a good it's a
good question. It goes to the question of why somebody on the
inside whispering secrets, you know, that's all.
Lastly I wonder about this, you know, this kind of fairy tale
quality aspect of the story is you're supplying food to your enemy.
Right, contemporary issue for sure of supplying, you know, aid to Gaza.
Oh, that's an interesting point. But though it's not food here per
se, the whole assumption is that they destroyed all the wheat fields
and all they're doing is allowing them to continue the worship. But
right, that's an interest. There you go. All right. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay. We're going to hit a few more of these stories with
מרדכי. Mordechai.
Now. הנהו שלש נשים דאייתו שלש קינין. hanu shalosh nashim d'aisu shalosh
kinin. So there were three women that showed up to the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash during this time and whether מרדכי Mordechai was still
around here. They all brought with them these קינין kinin which are
bird sacrifices. They always come in pairs of birds. Okay. חדא אמרה
לזיבתי. chada amra l'zivasi. One said, I'm bringing this for my זיבה,
ziva, for my flow. וחדא אמרה לימתי. v'chada amra l'yamasi. I'm bringing
this for my ocean, which also presumably means a heavy flow. וחדא
אמרה לעונתי. v'chada amra l'onasi.
I'm bringing this for my period.
So all of them sounded like they were bringing something relating to
some type of uterine bleeding, you know, and now you don't bring
a קרבן korban for being a נדה, nidda, you bring a קרבן
korban for being a זבה. zava. But maybe the assumption was that
they were all having different ways of euphemizing or, you know, that
they were זבות zavas and that the period was over and they
needed to bring a קרבן, korban, which seems reasonable. סבר מינה, savar
minah, they assumed זיבתי זבה ממש zivasi zava mamash means she's a
זבה, zava, right? It was this person a woman with a flow
not during the normal menstrual period but still a uterine flow. לימתי
לימתי ממש l'yamasi l'yamasi mamash literally my ocean, you know, again a
heavy flow. לעונתי לעונתה. l'onasi l'onasa. וכולהו חדא חטאת וחדא עולה. v'chulu
chada chatat v'chada ola. They're all different ways of describing that they're
having a blood flow and therefore it's a קרבן korban for a
זבה. zava. A זבה zava woman brings when the period is over,
seven days, clean days, one bird for a חטאת chatat and one
bird for an עולה. ola. אמר להו מרדכי, amar lehu Mordechai, so
מרדכי Mordechai was there and he said, wait a minute, שמא בזוב
סכנה, shema b'zove sichna, שמא בים סכנה, shema b'yam sichna, maybe it
has nothing to do with טומאה. tumah. Maybe it means that one
woman says that because of her flow she was, you know, she
had a health risk. Maybe it was a menstrual flow, not a
non-menstrual flow, and it's not a זבה. zava. So she's bringing a
קרבן korban because she had a health risk and she's now recovered
and she wants to do it as
a קרבן תודה, korban Toda, yeah, as an עולה, ola, a thanksgiving
to God. It has nothing to do with טומאה. tumah. And the
same one בים, b'yam, it may mean she's because of her flow
that she was endangered. And שמא בעונה סכנה. shema b'ona sichna. So
again the word ימ yam and עונה ona and זובה zova are
being explained the same but it's not to say she's a זבה
zava but to say she had a risky period relating to her
flow and now she's better and she's bringing this as an עולה.
ola. דכולהו עולות
נינהו. d'chulu olos ninhu. That they're both עולות, olos, not one עולה
ola and one חטאת. chatas. בדקו ואשכחו. badku v'ashk'chu. They checked and
they found out that he was right, that that was a good
that that was a good read. היינו דתנן. hainu d'tnan. That's what
we taught in the משנה, mishna, top of ס"ב עמוד א'. samech-bet
amud alef. פתחיה על הקינין פתחיה, Pitcha al ha-kinin Ptachia, excuse me,
פתחיה על הקינין. Ptachia al ha-kinin. So there was one of the
people who supervised the קינין, kinin, the bird sacrifices, his name was
פתחיה. Ptachia. And we say who is that?
זהו מרדכי. zeu Mordechai. That this was מרדכי. Mordechai. So that connects.
Now we have מרדכי Mordechai involved in, you know, in this discussion
about what the birds were being brought for. So we're connecting him
to this. Ptachya. And ולמה נקרא שמו פתחיה? V'lamah Nikrah Shemo Ptachya?
And if it was מרדכי, Mordechai, why would he be called פתחיה?
Ptachya? שפותח דברים
ודורשן. Shepoteach Devarim Vedorshan. Because as we've seen in the last two
Torahs, he was able to open up words and interpret them. He
was able to figure out what people were trying to get at
and what saying. ויודע בשבעים
לשון, Veyodea Beshivim Lashon, and he happened also to know all seventy
languages. So again, that's I guess what it means to be open,
to have access, to be able to interpret all different languages. The
גמרא Gemara says one minute, כולם סנהדרין נמי ידעי שבעים לשון? Kulu
Sanhedrin Nami Yad'ei Shivim Lashon? Wait a minute, what makes him so
special? Don't we say the entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin knows all seventy languages?
דאמר רבי יוחנן אין מושיבין בסנהדרין אלא בעלי חכמה בעלי מראה בעלי
קומה בעלי זקנה בעלי
כשפים. De'amar Rabbi Yochanan Ein Moshivin Besanhedrin Ela Ba'alei Chochma Ba'alei Mareh
Ba'alei Komah Ba'alei Ziknah Ba'alei Kshafim. The only people that get to
be on the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, presumably the סנהדרין הגדולה Sanhedrin Hagedolah seventy-one,
anyway, are people of wisdom, of good appearances, of height. So רש״י
Rashi says some of these is, you know, that they sort of
instill a sense of obedience and respect in the people that they're
ruling for. בעלי זקנה, Ba'alei Ziknah, elderly. בעלי כשפים, Ba'alei Kshafim, they
know witchcraft. Why is that? So רש״י Rashi says, well, you've learned
all these things, if you're judging a witch, they don't want the
witch to try to get out of the judgment through or whatever
or the male witch, the warlock, whatever, through the use of witchcraft.
So they have their own witchcraft as to counteract the witchcraft of
the
witch.
Right? תוספות Tosafot says a little bit less whatever,
a little more realistically, that if somebody is testifying or a related
case is related to witchcraft, they'll know what they're talking about, you
know, they're just educated in that so that they can understand what
the testimony is about. ויודעים שבעים לשון, Veyod'im Shivim Lashon, and know
all seventy languages. שלא תהא סנהדרין שומעת מפי המתורגמן Shelo Tehei Sanhedrin
Shome'at Mipi Hameturgeman so that you would not need a translator because
the translator can always, you know, you know, twist, intentionally or unintentionally,
what actually is being said. Now תוספות Tosafot by the way suggests,
really? Everybody knew all שבעים לשון? Shivim Lashon? So even if you
assume שבעים לשון Shivim Lashon is an exaggeration, תוספות Tosafot says well
maybe not everybody needed to know. Maybe it was enough that one
or two of them knew. And one or two of them would
hear directly and him you could trust to report to the rest
of the group what exactly was being said. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara
here is assuming it means everybody on the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So they're
saying what's special with מרדכי, Mordechai, especially if the assumption is that
this is originally מרדכי Mordechai and he was on the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
anyway? But everybody on the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, so why do you make
this big deal? So גמרא Gemara says, אלא Ellah you're
right, דהוה בלע לישני ודריש. Dehava Bala Lishnei Vedoresh. He would like
mix sort of languages together and be able to interpret them. דהיינו
דכתיב Dehainu Deketiv מרדכי בלשן, Mordechai Bilshan, that מרדכי Mordechai is בלשן.
Bilshan. And therefore we have that מרדכי Mordechai is also called
בלשן Bilshan in נחמיה Nechemia and now we, it does seem like
it's identifying it with the original מרדכי Mordechai because the גמרא Gemara
does identify him with בלשן Bilshan and it's the time period of
נחמיה Nechemia is at least more appropriate. So בלשן Bilshan is בולע
לשון, Bolela Lashon, mixed up the language. Now mixed up sounds like
it's the opposite of what we're trying to do, but whatever it
means, it means sort of think creatively about what's being said in
order to understand. Okay? What? בולע? Boloa? בולע? Boloa? בלשן? Bilshan? A
language. Right. Okay. So again, I don't know what to make of
the greater significance of this whole story other than it's interesting once
we're talking about מרדכי Mordechai to talk about his ability to interpret,
but you know, exactly so the larger significance, what you do have
obviously is the parallel that here's somebody who's able to unfold, interpret
language, signal appropriately, contrast it to the person who uses Greek wisdom
to do it. And you know, as I said, I think the
larger theme is, it's about sort of the use and misuse of
proper and improper messages. So you know, there's nothing bad about being
able to sort of, you know, you know, know tricks of communication
and understand and you know, sort of, you know, figure out, you
know, the hidden meaning of what people are saying if you use
it correctly. So מרדכי Mordechai here is using it to help bring
the right קרבנות Korbanot to figure out where you bring the עומר
Omer and the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem from. Right? The problem is
when you use those things and you use them to communicate to
the people outside and have them send the pig inside. You know,
and the same idea that the very idea of like I was
saying is that the pig also very almost represents somebody that sort
of presenting themselves properly but ultimately it's something, you know, bad and
evil and here, you know, you're trying to be the king. But
so I think it's the question about the mixing up of messages
which maybe are themselves, you know, neutral and not intrinsically bad, but
the question is, you know, what, how are they, how are they
being used. So that's what I think is sort of the larger
theme going on here, yes. So actually when you're saying that not
all needed to know the seventy languages, so what does this אין
מושיבין בסנהדרין אלא Ein Moshivin Besanhedrin Ela this, that? No, תוספות Tosafot
tries to just be a little more realistic, but the simple פשט
Pshat of the גמרא Gemara here admits that they all needed to
know. Okay. So now we go on to the next משנה Mishna
now that we had that fascinating story about the use of Greek
wisdom whatever that meant, and about the whole the sending up of
the pig. Now we go to the next משנה. Mishna. כיצד הם
עושים? Keitzad Hein Osim? How would they actually harvest the barley for
the עומר? Omer? First even if it's not שבת Shabbat and in
a minute we're going to talk about what if it is שבת.
Shabbat. Okay, so what would they do? Right? We sort of left
שבת Shabbat behind already in the last משנה Mishna about bringing them
nearby was no longer about שבת. Shabbat. We never actually answered that,
what would they do on שבת, Shabbat, right? There was like three
people or whatever. Let's focus. Okay, now what would they do? שלוחי
בית דין יוצאים מערב יום טוב, Shluchei Beit Din Yotzin Me'erev Yom
Tov, so שלוחי בית דין Shluchei Beit Din would go out on
ערב יום טוב Erev Yom Tov ועושים אותן כריכות. Ve'osim Otan Krichot.
They would sort of wrap a band around some wheat that was
still attached, and they want to make it easy to cut afterwards,
so they would spend time before יום טוב. Yom Tov. We're going
to see that יסוד, yesod, you do the cutting on the day
itself. That was the, that's how it's derived on the פסוק. pasuk.
You do the cutting on the day of the עומר. Omer. But
you don't want to waste time that you don't have to. So
you spend time before יום טוב Yom Tov identifying where's the grain
you want to cut, you wrap it together in a way that
the סימן, siman, and then afterwards you're going to go out right
after יום טוב, Yom Tov, the day of the עומר, Omer, and
you'll go right there and cut it immediately. And for some people
that's why the idea of making a little mark in the חלה
Challah before you make
המוציא, Hamotzi, so that after you make the ברכה, bracha, you're not
trying to decide where should I cut from and there's a הפסק
hefsek to have the mark, you start at the mark. Of course,
as we know what happens is you make the ברכה bracha and
you say, now where's that mark that I put in? So it
doesn't really help. But what?
Then it would turn. Anyway, okay. So that they would do that
beforehand while it was still attached, כדי שיהא נוח לקצור, k’dei sheyehei
no’ach liktzor, it would be easy to cut when it came the
time, the day after יום טוב. Yom Tov. כל העיירות הסמוכות לשם
מתכנסות לשם, kol ha’ayaros hasmuchos l’sham miskansos l’sham, all the villages nearby
that field would gather in that field כדי שיהא נקצר בעסק גדול,
k’dei sheyehei niktzar b’esek gadol, and that it should be cut in
a big hubbub, a big deal, a big to-do. Okay, now why?
We'll see in a minute that the whole idea was to publicize
which is the day for cutting the עומר Omer and starting the
count of the ספירה Sefira in order to also publicize which is
the day that's going to be שבועות Shavuos be fifty days hence.
And because that was all debated between them and the other sectarians,
you know, about when do you, what is ממחרת השבת? mimacharas haShabbos?
So they made a point of making a very big to-do about
it that it was publicized. And I would say not only publicized,
but as we're about to see in this description, that it was
a, that it was like a consensus. No, a consensus. They're going
to shape it as if everybody here, it's universally known and everybody
knows we do it this way, and so on to sort of
frame the other opinion as marginal, as you know, marginal and a
trivial opinion. So they're framing this as the consensus. Okay, so let's
take a look. כיון
שחשכה, keivan she’chashecha,
now it became nightfall. The point is like this. It's now sixteenth
of ניסן. Nissan. If you wait till the morning, the morning is
when you bring the עומר. Omer. You want the עומר Omer ready
to be brought first thing in the morning, so you cut it
the night before, which is halachically the same day. So we understand
that the cutting has to be on the day of bringing, but
the time you cut it the night before the day of bringing,
which is halachically the day, so you can bring it on that
day. How do they see? They had, yeah, exactly. They took flares.
כיון שחשכה, keivan she’chashecha, אמר להן, amar lahen, so he said to
the villagers, whoever was in charge, what? Amos? Ah. Yeah, he said
to the villagers all around, אמר להן, amar lahen, בא השמש, ba
hashemesh, has the sun set? אומרים, omrim, they all said הן, hen,
yes. בא השמש, ba hashemesh, has the sun set? אומרים, omrim, הן,
hen, they all say yes. מגל זו, magal zu, should I use
this scythe? אומרים, omrim, הן, hen, they said yes. מגל זו, magal
zu, should I use this? אומרים, omrim, הן, hen, they said yes.
קופה זו, kuppah zu, should I use this basket? אומרים, omrim, הן,
hen, yes. קופה זו, kuppah zu, should I use this basket? אומרים,
omrim, הן, hen, they said yes. Now as it happened to be
בשבת, beShabbos, if they were doing it on שבת, Shabbos, אומר, omer,
שבת זו, Shabbos zu, should I do it even today if שבת?
Shabbos? אומרים, omrim, הן, hen, they said yes. שבת זו, Shabbos zu,
should I, this שבת Shabbos I should cut? אומרים, omrim, הן, hen,
they said yes. אקצור, ektzor, now so okay, I'm all ready. Should
I now start cutting? והם אומרים לו, veheim omrim lo, קצור, ktzor,
cut. אקצור, ektzor, should I cut? והם אומרים לו, veheim omrim lo,
קצור. ktzor. שלוש פעמים על כל דבר ודבר, shalosh pe’amim al kol
davar vedavar, three times they did this whole thing. Not clear because
each thing he said twice. I know. Each twice, three times, so
it's total asking six times or was it... anyway, either way. ובהן
הם אומרים, uve’hen heim omrim, הן הן הן, hen hen hen, yes,
yes, yes. Why? כל כך למה? kol kach lamah? Why? מפני הבייתוסין,
mipnei haBaysusin, because of the בייתוסין. Baysusin. We don't hear of them
too much, normally we hear about the צדוקין. Tzadokim. But here it's
identified with
בייתוסין. Baysusin. שהיו אומרים, she’hayu omrim, אין קצירת העומר במוצאי יום טוב.
ein ktziras ha’omer b’motzei yom tov. You don't do it on the
sixteenth, you do it on ממחרת השבת, mimacharas haShabbos, on a Sunday.
And therefore they made a big thing. And I'm saying it's not
just a big like proclamation, hey we're doing it. But it's done
in a way that like he's asking and everybody agrees, you know,
it's the consensus, and having, you know, any normal person knows that
you do it today. It's only you crazies that you have a
different idea. Okay, I think it's really done specifically to shape it
as a consensus. Okay,
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, now we taught. And it's not exactly a
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, it's a quote from מגילת תענית. Megillas Ta’anis.
מגילת
תענית Megillas Ta’anis is a, is a, you know, is an ancient
book written in the בית שני Bayis Sheini period, which lists the
days that you don't, you're not allowed to fast on, the minor
holidays, because of a lot of like minor events that happened at
the time that at the time were, were historically, were significant, don't
have big lasting historical significance, but they were recorded there as days
not to fast on, and some days that were particularly important not
even to למספד l’mispas on. By the way, that's where we get
the story of חנוכה Chanukah was it's recorded there in מגילת תענית
Megillas Ta’anis that those are eight days that you do not fast
on or למספד l’mispas on. So here's what we have from מגילת
תענית. Megillas Ta’anis.
אילין יומיא דלא להתענא בהון, ilin yomaya d’la l’isana b’hon, the following
days you don't fast on. ומקצתהון דלא למספד בהון, umiktzathon d’la l’mispas
b’hon, and some are so
weighty that you don't eulogize on. מריש ירחא דניסן עד תמניא ביה,
me’reish yarcha d’Nissan ad tamnya beih, from Rosh Chodesh Nissan until the
eighth, איתוקם תמידא, isokam tamida, the... The bringing of the תמיד Tamid
was established. We'll see what that means, there was a whole debate
and it was established the way the תמיד Tamid was brought, and
that was a holiday דלא למספד d'lo le'mispid that you would and
it's so important you don't even eulogize. מתימניא ביה ועד סוף מועדא
Mi'tamnaya beh v'ad sof moada from the eighth of Nissan until the
end of the מועד moed of the end of Pesach, איתותב חגא
דשבועיא, itotav chaga d'shavuaya, it was established the holiday of שבועות, Shavuot,
the Pharisees won their debate with the בייתוסין Baitusin and it was
established
that in
practice they minimized the opposition that שבועות Shavuot you start bringing from
the עומר Omer on the sixteenth of Nissan. Where are we?
דלא למספד d'lo le'mispid okay, דלא למספד d'lo le'mispid that you would
not eulogize. Now if you look at the side the גרסא girsa
is not דלא למספד d'lo le'mispid but דלא להתענא. d'lo le'itana. It
was not as big of a victory and rather than saying not
to eulogize they only said and Rashi and Tosafot both have this
גרסא girsa here and it's a whole question in different גמרות, Gemarot,
anyway not to fast. So one thing we'll talk about later is
which was the greater victory and why, but for now we'll pause
on that. Let's take a look at the debate itself. מריש ירחא
דניסן ועד תמניא ביה Meresh Yarcha d'Nissan v'ad tamne beh from ראש
חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan until the eighth, איתוקם תמידא דלא למספד,
it'ukom tamida d'lo le'mispid,
the תמיד Tamid was established and therefore you do not have eulogize.
What was the issue with the תמיד? Tamid? שהיו צדוקים אומרים, She'hayu
Tzedukim omrim, the Sadducees would say יחיד מתנדב ומביא תמיד, yachid mitnadev
umevi tamid, an individual can bring his own תמיד. Tamid. מאי דרוש,
Mai darush, where did they get this from? את הכבש האחד תעשה
בבוקר, Et hakeves ha'echad ta'ase baboker, you in the singular shall bring
the one lamb in the morning, ואת הכבש השני תעשה בין הערבים.
v'et hakeves hasheni ta'ase bein ha'arbayim. So therefore an individual can bring.
Now what does it mean? Why is it not just considered an
עולה? olah? But maybe it means that I'm going to say today
I'm going to dedicate the תמיד Tamid with my money. Today's תמיד
Tamid has been sponsored by so-and-so. Okay, so that's what the צדוקים
Tzedukim said. Okay, תעשה בין הערבים. ta'ase bein ha'arbayim.
So מאי אהדרו ליה, mai ahadro leh, what did they respond, how'd
they disprove it? Because it says את קרבני לחמי לאשי תשמרו, Et
korbani lachmi l'ishai tishmeru, you collectively should observe my קרבנות, korbanot, my
communal קרבנות, korbanot, שכולם באים מתרומת הלשכה, she'kulam ba'im mitrumat halishka, they
all have to come from communal coffers. I know, so yeah that
was it, that was all they could say back. And on the
other thing is besides which that sometimes singular means you as a
collective, right. No or it means that you could just make sure
that it's brought, forget about who sponsored it. Anyway somehow that was
seen that they won the debate, right? I also think it's interesting
and obviously this is just my speculation is that there's a little
subtext that notes it's the צדוקים Tzedukim that are trying to break
away from the communal reality, right? You're trying to say an individual
can sort of impose his will and identify have his have it
his קרבן korban and not the communal קרבן. korban. It's sort of
I think the whole idea that they're the way חז"ל Chazal are
framing it, right? Who's the sectarian is always depending who you're asking,
history is like written by the winners, right? So the way חז"ל
Chazal are framing it they're the Judaism and everybody else is the
sectarians.
So therefore they're saying the same way by the עומר Omer that
was the consensus and crazy people that had a different version, so
here too it's the צדוקים, Tzedukim, they want to do something they
want to take it away from the communal reality from the consensus,
they want it to be like an individual קרבן korban and not
a communal קרבן. korban. Anyway that's just my little subtext read which
you can take it or leave it. What did it take them
eight days to respond? Why the? It was a debate that went
on for eight days and somehow in the end I don't know
nobody knows. Obviously a lot of this has a lot less to
do with the substance of the argument and probably a lot more
to do with various other types of political and other factors in
terms of who wins these debates. Right, it didn't seem like a
convincing retort. Right, it takes eight days like what one day we
establish. No yeah it was somehow some type of a debate that
lasted eight days. Okay. Right exactly whatever it is. All right, so
now it goes on it says like this. That was that one.
Now we get to שבועות. Shavuot. Okay,
מתימניא ביה ועד סוף מועדא, Mi'tamnaya beh v'ad sof moada, from the
eighth of Nissan until the end of Pesach they were debating שבועות.
Shavuot. איתותב חגא דשבועיא, itotav chaga d'shavuaya, they established the holiday of
שבועות, Shavuot, דלא למספד d'lo le'mispid and therefore we don't eulogize or
we don't fast during that period of time. Why was that? שהיו
בייתוסין אומרים, She'hayu Baitusin omrim, the בייתוסין Baitusin were saying עצרת אחר
השבת, Atzeret achar haShabbat, that שבועות Shavuot falls out on a Sunday
because you start the עומר Omer on a
Sunday, presumably the first Sunday after the first day of Pesach. Okay.
נטפל להם רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Nitpal lahem Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai.
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai was assigned to them. But again נטפל להם
nitpal lahem from the word טפל taphel means it was trivial and
the whole point that verb already signals that he's not treating them
seriously like he's just humoring them.
Okay, נטפל להם רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, nitpal lahem Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai, he sort pretended to tag along to them. No no let's
take a look. ואמר להם V'amar lahem and he said to them
שוטים, shotim, idiots. That's a good way to start a conversation. Idiots!
מנין לכם, minayin lachem, where do you get this idea from that
you start on Sunday? I don't know the פסוק pasuk says ממחרת
השבת. mimmacharat haShabbat. Okay, but somehow he already starts by casting their
position as completely absurd. Where do you get this crazy idea? Okay.
ולא היה אדם אחד שהיה משיבם, V'lo haya adam echad she'haya meshivam,
nobody. Idiots. That's a good way to start a conversation. Idiots. מנין
לכם, Minayin lachem, where do you think, where do you get this
idea from that you start on Sunday? I don't know, the פסוק
pasuk says ממחרת השבת. Mimochoras Hashabbos. Okay, but somehow you already start
by casting their position as completely absurd. Where do you get this
crazy idea from? Okay, והיה אדם אחד שהיה משיבו... V'haya adam echad
shehaya meshivo... ולא היה אדם אחד שהיה משיבו? v'lo haya adam echad
shehaya meshivo? Nobody was willing to hazard... Again, probably not because they
didn't have a good פסוק pasuk that said
ממחרת השבת, Mimochoras Hashabbos, but if the people in charge are sort
of saying idiots, where do you get this from, who wants to
get into that type of debate? Right, the deck is a little
loaded. Okay,
חוץ מזקן אחד chutz mizaken echad here again is if there's an
elder, there's an elder again, שהיה מפטפט כנגדו. shehaya mepatpet knegdo. He
was like sputtering, not sputtering, you know whatever, he was like whatever
word would be stuttering, but like you know like chattering or whatever.
You know again it's not a it's not a positive way, it's
sort of saying you know he's like sputtering, sputtering would be the
idea. Okay, opposite he was willing to go against יוחנן בן זכאי.
Yochanan ben Zakkai. אומר Omer what?
Blubbering blubbering. Sim, yeah, okay, well I think maybe a little more
like sputtering like tut tut tut like he was just saying silly
things like okay anyway, he was willing to take his position and
אמר amar and look at his position where he doesn't even quote
the
פסוק pasuk from the שבועות. Shavuot. No, and אמר משה רבינו אוהב
ישראל היה. amar Moshe Rabbeinu ohev Yisrael haya. What? It happened. Right.
As long as you're on the winner's side. Okay. משה רבינו Moshe
Rabbeinu loved the Jewish people ויודע ששבועות יום אחד הוא. veyodeia sheShavuot
yom echad hu. He knew that שבועות Shavuot was only one day,
נבך nebach it's a holiday for only one day, you know anybody
who's lived in in חוץ לארץ Chutz la'aretz will tell you how
important it is to at least have two days of every יום
טוב. yom tov. עמד והתקינה אחר שבת, Amad vehitkina achar Shabbos, so
he made sure that שבועות Shavuot would fall out on a
Sunday כדי שישראל מתענגין שני ימים kedei sheYisrael miamgin shenei yamim so
at least they could have two days to celebrate
שבועות. Shavuot. קרא עליו מקרא זה, Kara alav mikra zeh, so יוחנן
בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai responded, he quoted the following פסוק: pasuk:
אחד עשר יום מחורב דרך הר שעיר. achad asar yom meChorev derech
Har Seir. It says that you know the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
was 11 days from הר סיני. Har Sinai. אם משה רבינו אוהב
ישראל היה, Im Moshe Rabbeinu ohev Yisrael haya, according to you that
משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu loved the Jewish people and of course according
to you everybody assumes that he loved the Jewish people, but according
to you that he's willing to do anything in order to you
know for the sake of the Jewish people למה איחרם במדבר ארבעים
שנה? lama icharam bamidbar arbaim shana? Why did he make them wander
for forty years? It was 11 days to get to ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. Well obviously what kind of an answer is that? He
didn't care about the Jewish people and your whole thing was a
stupid proof and was a stupid answer. Okay fine. אמר לו, Amar
lo, so he said to Rabbi בקיפח אתה פוטרני, bakifach ata potrani,
that's how you are dismissing me with that type of a response?
At least give me a serious response. אמר לו Amar lo said
בחשום שוטה, Bakhshum shoteh, idiot again, good way to frame the debate,
שלא תהא תורה שלמה שלנו כשיחה בטילה שלכם. shelo tehei Torah shleima
shelanu kesicha betela shelachem.
Our pure complete תורה Torah is not you know is not equatable
with your stupid speech. So we can't have we can't have a
discussion. We have the truth, you have your idiotic ideas, you know
I'm not even going to bother to deign it with a response.
Okay powerful.
You are very deeply offended right. Well on
behalf of fellow Jews? No I don't. Well they have important religious
points to be making and they look part of the problem here
is that the פסוקים pesukim read quite nicely I'd say literally on
Sunday right פשט pshat of the פסוקים. pesukim. So maybe the only
way that if you know you believe in your tradition but you
know that they have a pretty strong argument on the opposite way
maybe you have to maybe skew this the debate in order that
you can sort of you know win be persuasive you know so
that's I mean it's not pleasant but that sort of seems to
be what's going on which gets to the question of which was
the greater holiday. רש"י Rashi says ironically that the reason שבועות Shavuot
was the winning of this battle of שבועות Shavuot was less significant
according to גזירה gezeira you don't fast but you are allowed to
eulogize is because well that was such an easy battle to win
I mean come on there's so many פסוקים pesukim that we're going
to bring in a minute to prove how we know שבועות Shavuot
is the sixth you know you start on the how you start
on the 16th of ניסן Nissan and of course you could have
said the exact opposite which is sort of what תוספות Tosafos says
which is it wasn't such an easy battle to win and the
and the victory wasn't so conclusive so therefore we're not going to
make it such a huge victory the same way we made the
other thing a huge victory. So you know there's a whole question
here was this seen as a bigger victory an easier victory or
less conclusive victory and we're now going to spend the remainder of
the דף daf trying to prove what you know יוחנן בן זכאי
Yochanan ben Zakkai is taking as being so patently obvious not so
patently obvious and we're going to try to use the remainder of
the דף daf to try to prove it. Right did you want
to say something before I go on? Abba? When
when we use this kind of language that just some of us
islanded away yeah so not nice. What is bullying? That's
the word yeah.
Is there any comment about that or is that just considered
appropriate? No it's hard to find people that are sympathizing with the
ביתוסים Boethusians in the rabbinic literature. Nobody discusses nobody says like well
maybe you're right but why use that language? No but again what
I think it really is reflective of is that you know it's
like the guy the famous joke they say somebody gave a speech
they walked up to the podium afterwards they found his note card
and written in one of the margins was argument weak speak quickly.
So it's like you know so it's like argument weak speak harshly.
So okay you don't have you know in the end you might
not be able to win on substance so you've got to... little
bit silence the opposition. That's your interpretation. That's my view of this,
right? The standard. Correct. Everybody, I mean, again, רש״י Rashi said they
didn't make such a חג chag of it because it was such
an easy win, which is so bizarre. תוספות Tosafot disagrees with that.
Okay, so let's see a little bit now in the גמרא Gemara
really tries to prove it. There's a rabbi in the community that
I used to go to frequently that I quickly learned that whenever
he said, now listen carefully, in one of his שיעורים, shiurim, that's
when he was going to make a
logical point. And he said listen carefully so you would think, oh,
I didn't listen carefully. So
there you go. But yes, I don't know what the גמרא Gemara
is going to conclude here, but my guess is that the arguments
actually could probably be won on a textual basis or whatever you
want to call it by תוספות. Tosafot. Right, that was my point.
That's what I was saying. Yeah, that they reduced the substance of
the argument. It's hard to win in terms of, right, the modern-day
implications are quite striking. For what? We're still arguing the argument's going
by תורה שבעל פה, Torah she'ba'al peh, it's going by מסורה. mesorah.
I mean, you engage with these theological
arguments or arguments להלכה l'halacha with reform, God forbid. Oh, I see.
Oh,
and you think that they have more of a convincing
argument even though you know that from your perspective what they're saying
is wrong? You don't want to lose them based on this issue
of מסורה. mesorah. Right, right. This way or that way, right. Well,
why doesn't he say that then? Well, that's not going to win
because the whole point is they're debating what the מסורה mesorah is,
or debating whether, I mean, they don't buy into that מסורה. mesorah.
Okay, so let's take on, so let's take a look.
Okay, כתוב אחד אומר, kasuv echad omer, so now here we're going
to start actually proving it. כתוב אחד אומר, kasuv echad omer, one
פסוק pasuk says: תספרו חמישים יום, tispru chamishim yom, count fifty days;
וכתוב אחד אומר, v'kasuv echad omer, and one פסוק pasuk says: שבע
שבתות תמימות תהיינה, sheva shabbatot temimot tihyena, seven full weeks. הקיצד, ha-keitzad,
how do you satisfy
both פסוקים? psukim?
So, כאן ביום טוב שחל להיות בשבת כאן ביום טוב שחל להיות
באמצע
שבת, kan b'Yom Tov she'chal liyos b'Shabbos kan b'Yom Tov she'chal liyos
b'emtza Shabbos, whether יום טוב Yom Tov fell out on שבת Shabbos
or during the week. Why? Because שבע שבתות תמימות, sheva shabbatot temimot,
full weeks, the גמרא Gemara understands means the week that starts on
Sunday. So one פסוק pasuk says you can get full weeks. How
can you get full weeks? If יום טוב Yom Tov falls out
on שבת, Shabbos, then you start the counting on Sunday, which makes
the בייתוסים Baitusim happy. But it says it's not always going to
be full weeks. Sometimes you're just going to have a count of
days and not a count of full weeks, and that'll be when
יום טוב Yom Tov falls out on any other day of the
week and you're going to start not on a Sunday but on
a different day. Why don't you say 49 days?
Oh, well, okay, I have to be clear. It's because of ממחרת
השבת. mimacharat ha'Shabbos. Right. Because we don't have to count from שבת
Shabbos all the time. Right, well, that's the point. If שבת Shabbos
means יום טוב, Yom Tov, it's not always going to be full
weeks. So therefore, the idea of full weeks that's for the בייתוסים
Baitusim deals with the problem, surprisingly not in the גמרא, Gemara, why
it says 50 days if it's only 49. Okay, תוספות Tosafot basically
has two answers and there's a רא״ש Rosh that has a third.
What תוספות Tosafot answer is basically, one is 50 days means until
the 50th day and then on the 50th not... עד ולא עד
בכלל. ad v'lo ad bichlal. Okay, or another answer which is more
or less the same
is: עד ממחרת השבת השביעית תספרו חמישים יום והקרבתם מנחה חדשה להשם.
ad mimacharat ha'shabbos ha'shvi'is tispru chamishim yom v'hikravtem mincha chadasha l'Hashem. Day
50 is שבועות, Shavuos, but not תספרו חמישים יום. tispru chamishim yom.
The רא״ש Rosh says, amazingly, that the תורה's Torah rounding, the same
way when the תורה Torah says 40 lashes, חז״ל Chazal interpret this
to mean 39, so the 50 really means 49. But it's interesting
that the whole point that the תורה Torah says 50, we count
49 days, is not discussed in the גמרא, Gemara, it's discussed by
the ראשונים. Rishonim. Yes. But who are these בייתוסים? Baitusim? What? Could
this be maybe very beginning of Christianity? There has to be some
more info. In Greek civilization?
Maybe. I mean, but the sectarianism began well before Christianity. I mean,
Christianity itself started as a Jewish sect, so I wouldn't put it
in necessarily in that context. Okay, well let me just read one
more line. Okay, so let's just read one more line. רבי אליעזר
אומר אינו צריך, Rabbi Eliezer omer eino tzarich, you don't need to
learn it from there, I'll learn it from another
פסוק. pasuk. אינו צריך הרי הוא אומר תספור לך, eino tzarich harei
hu omer tispor lacha, count for you, so again, different than what
we said before that the singular language means individual, here we're saying
what חז״ל's Chazal more general approach is, that the singular language refers
to כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael as a corporate entity. So therefore it
says you shall count, תספור לך, tispor lacha, so it means you,
the singular entity, should count. Now, how does that happen? So it
says not as individuals. ספירה תלויה בבית דין, sfira tluya b'Beis Din,
so it's dependent on the בית דין, Beis Din, שהן יודעים לחדש
ממחרת השבת ממחרת יום טוב. she'hen yodim l'chadesh mimacharat ha'Shabbos mimacharat Yom
Tov. They know when the day after שבת Shabbos is because it's
the day after יום טוב. Yom Tov. יצאת שבת בראשית, yatzas Shabbos
bereishis, which excludes the normal
שבת, Shabbos, שספירה בכל אדם, she'sfira b'chol adam, that every individual does
it. What's he saying? He's saying like this. Since in one place
normally it says וספרתם לכם, u'sfartem lachem, which actually from which we
learn that it's not a counting done by בית דין, Beis Din,
it's counting that each individual does. The use of the plural leads
each and every individual. But in one of the places it says
תספור לך. tispor lach. singular, to be somehow this counting is dependent
on something that is done by כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael*. Now what's
done by כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael* or בית דין *Beis Din* representing
כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael*? Making שבת *Shabbos* isn't done by כלל ישראל
*Klal Yisrael* determining which day שבת *Shabbos* is, that happens naturally. But
if the counting it takes place in reference to פסח *Pesach* and
that in reference to when the new month was established, then that's
a counting that is dependent on the act of כלל ישראל *Klal
Yisrael* on the act of בית דין *Beis Din* who determine when
the months are. So because of the use of the singular, he
said it's dependent on when the months are established and therefore we
know it's dependent on פסח *Pesach* and not dependent on שבת *Shabbos*.
So we will continue tomorrow more proofs of this obvious point that
פסח *Pesach* שבועות *Shavuos* starts and the עומר *Omer* begins the day
after יום טוב *Yom Tov* and not the day after
שבת *Shabbos*.